A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, RG 5 Program Files, Subgroup Grant Files FA1795
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Education, 1986-2004; 7; 23.17 Cubic Feet 61 letter document boxes
  - Gallaudet University, 9800036, 1998 March 17-1999 March 17 (Box 48, Folder 1)
    Grant 9800036, $50,000.00, for an excellence in education transition grant to develop distance learning and school-based applied research components.
  - Hampshire College, 9800187, 1998 December 8-1999 December 8 (Box 48, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2187
    Grant 9800187, $150,000.00, for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - Haverford College, 9800034, 1998 March 17-1999 March 17 (Box 48, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 2188
    Grant 9800034, $15,000.00, for an excellence in education transition grant to disseminate a workbook developed by the Inquiry in Science and Math project.
  - Heritage College, 97-80, 1997 March 18-1999 March 18 (Box 48, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 2189
    Grant 97-80, $135,000.00, for transition funding to make the Knight-Scholars teacher education program self-sustaining through consolidation with the Indian Education Summer Institute.
  - Reed College, 9800189, 1998 December 8-1999 December 8 (Box 49, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 2192
    Grant 9800189, $150,000.00 for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - University of Akron Foundation, 97-83, 1997 March 18-1999 March 19 (Box 50, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 2194
    Grant 97-83, University of Akron Foundation, $100,000 for transition funding for project AAMP (Akron: Achieving Mathematical Proficiency) to conduct a more extensive evaluation, expand from grades six-10 to grades six-12, and enhance community awareness.
  - Dade Public Education Fund Inc., 87-104, 1987 June 26-1988 June 26 (Box 50, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3035
    Grant 87-104, Dade Public Education Fund Inc., $20,000 to expand a program of mini-grants to principals in the Dade County Public Schools
  - Easter Seal Society of Dade County Inc., 87-148, 1987 September 25-1988 September 25 (Box 50, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 3036
    Grant 87-148, Easter Seal Society of Dade County Inc., $100,000 for a capital campaign
  - James H. Hammond Academy, 87-238, 1987 December 15-1988 December 15 (Box 51, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3045
    Grant 87-238, James H. Hammond Academy, $10,000 to equip five new science laboratories for elementary and secondary students.
  - La Salle University, 87-11, 1987 June 26-1988 June 26 (Box 51, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 3047
    Grant 87-111, La Salle University, $15,000 for the M.A. program in bilingual/bicultural studies (spanish) for educators and other urban professionals.
  - Leon County Schools, 87-49, 1987 March 27-1988 March 27 (Box 51, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3048
    Grant 87-49, Leon County Schools, $9,000 for the North Florida writing project, a teacher training center.
  - Living Arts and Science Center, 87-227, 1987 December 15-1988 December 15 (Box 51, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3049
    Grant 87-227, Living Arts and Science Center, $15,000 for an elevator and housing to make this museum and teaching center accessible to handicapped children.
  - Northern State University, 87-186, 1987 September 25-1988 September 25 (Box 51, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 3055
    Grant 87-186, Northern State University, $5,000 to assist in the construction of a hall of fame VIP room in the Joseph Barnett physical education and convocation center.
  - San Jose State University Foundation, 87-204, 1987 December 15-1988 December 15 (Box 52, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3062
    Grant 87-204, San Jose State University Foundaiton, $285,000 for a communication skills and technical wrtiting production laboratory in the engineering complex.
  - Transylvania University, 87-87, 1987 June 26-1988 June 30 (Box 52, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 3066
    Grant 87-87, Transylvania University, $50,000 for general support.
  - United Negro College Fund Inc., 87-156, 1987 June 25-1988 June 25 (Box 52, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 3067
    Grant 87-156, United Negro College Fund Inc., $40,000 for annual support.
  - University of Akron Foundation, 87-188, 1987 June 25-1988 June 25 (Box 52, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 3068
    Grant 87-188, University of Akron Foundation, $5,000 for the partners in excellence.
  - Aberdeen Area Literacy Council, 88-110, 1988 June 30-1989 June 30 (Box 53, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3074
    Grant 88-110, Aberdeen Area Literacy Council, $12,125 for general support.
  - Florida State University Foundation Inc., 87-270, 1988 February 1-1989 February 1 (Box 53, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 3077
    Grant 87-270, Florida State University Foundation Inc., $72,000 for research project "an investigation of the effects of newspaper-based instruction on reading comprehension in an at-risk secondary grade level population" - no portion to be used for university overhead. Project extended from June 1989 to September 1989 upon the request of the university.
  - University of Akron Foundation, 87-81, 1987 June 26-1989 June 30 (Box 53, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 3081
    Grant 87-81, University of Akron Foundation, $500,000 for planning and related initial costs of acquiring and converting the former Polsky department store into an academic center which can benefit both the University and downtown Akron.
  - The University of Maryland Foundation Inc., 87-73, 1987 March 27-1989 March 31 (Box 53, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 3082
    Grant 87-73, The University of Maryland Foundation Inc., $850,000 for mid-career training for journalists.
  - University of Miami, 86-144, 1986 December 19-1990 December 31 (Box 54, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3084
    Grant 86-144, University of Miami, $500,000 for the Miami Project, a concentrated attack on the problem of paralysis due to spinal cord injury.
  - University of Michigan - Ann Arbor, 87-74, 1987 March 27-1991 March 31 (Box 54, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 3089
    Grant 87-74, University of Michigan - Ann Arbor, $500,000 for the Knight Business Fellowship and the Knight medical fellowship for journalists.
  - University of Missouri Systems, 87-77, 1987 March 27-1991 March 31 (Box 55, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3090
    Grant 87-77, University of Missouri Systems, $541,100 to support a five-year pilot project to increase the number of minority students in journalism.
  - The University of North Dakota, 92-329, 94-112, 1992 December 15-1996 December 18 (Box 55, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 2359
    Grant 92-329, $252,000 to establish professional development schools at one elementary and one junior high school, resulting in curriculum revision in both schools and the university's teacher education program. Also includes a 94-112 supplemental grant of $5,000 for travel funds for conferences.
  - The University of Pennsylvania, 92-341, 94-113, 1992 December 15-1996 December 16 (Box 55, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 2360
    Grant 92-341, $252,000 to aid the Philadelphia School System in developing an evaluation process for shared decision-making and school-based management in restructured elementary and middle schools. Also includes a 94-113 supplemental grant of $5,000 for travel funds for conferences.
  - American Council on Education, 9900090, 1999 June 15-2000 June 15 (Box 56, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 3117
    Grant 9900090, American Council on Education, $250,000, for the College Is Possible Campaign, a two-pronged initiative to educate prospective students and their families better about the accessibility of higher education and financial aid and to promote cost effectiveness in higher education.
  - Charlotte-Mecklenburg Schools, 9900066, 1999 June 15-2000 June 15 (Box 56, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 3122
    Grant 9900066, Charlotte-Mecklenburg Schools, $90,000, To implement the IMPACT II teacher development and networking model in the Charlotte-Mecklenburg Schools.
  - Communities in Schools, Inc., 96-223, 1996 September 17-2000 September 17 (Box 57, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3126
    Grant 96-223, Communities in Schools, Inc. $1,500,000 for partial challenge grant to implement and assess the national training expansion program including technical assistance for efforts in knight foundation communitites.
  - Heritage College, 9900023, 1999 March 16-2000 March 16 (Box 58, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3132
    Grant 9900023, Heritage College, $50,000 for gathering 99, an event to share the distinctive approaches to multicultural education developed by this college serving large numbers of native american and hispanic students.
  - Morehouse College, 9900310, 1999 December 7-2000 December 7 (Box 58, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 2361
    Grant 9900310 for Morehouse College for $150,000 for a Presidential Leadership grant.
  - National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Inc., 9700170, 1997 December 9-2000 December 9 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3139
    Grant 9700170, National Board for Professional Teaching Standards Inc., $909,000 to develop a community-based collaborative model in Charlotte utilizing the national board's standards as the basis for teacher professional development and teacher education.
  - Communities in schools of Wichita, 1998 June 15-2001 June 15 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3155
    Grant 9800101, Communitites in schools of Wichita /Sedgewick County, $150,000 to develop and implement a comprehensive evaluation plan including the use of the School Success Profile.
  - Executive Service Corps of the Delaware Valley, 2000 December 5-2001 December 5 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 3156
    Grant 20000263, Executive Service Corps of the Delaware Valley, $24,600 for management of volunteer consulting services for local public schools.
  - Florida Agricultural & Mechanical University Foundation,9800037, 1998 March 17-2001 March 17 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 3157
    Grant 9800037, Florida Agricultural & Mechanical University Foundation (FAMU) $200,000 for an excellence in Education transition grant to evaluate the Accelerated Schools reform model and to test the Read, Write and Type instructional program as a means for improving reading achievement.
  - Mayor's Commission on Literacy, 2000 June 13-2001 June 13 (Box 62, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3162
    Grant 20000128, Mayor's Commission on Literacy, $65,000 for the families that work Workforce Literacy Project in conjunction with the National Center for Family Literacy's Family Independence Initiative linking family literacy services to welfare-to-work reform.
  - Reach Out and Read, 20000057, 2000 March 14-2001 March 14 (Box 63, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3168
    Grant 20000057, Reach Out and Read, $647,000 to expand programs in Charlotte, Philadelphia and Palm Beach County and to collaborate in the development of strategies for community literacy in Charlotte and South Florida.
  - Summit Education Initiative, 2000 June 13-2001 June 13 (Box 63, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 3170
    Grant 20000144, Summit Education Initiative, $1 million for program and operational support.
  - University of Kentucky Research Foundation, 9800250, 1998 December 8-2001 December 8 (Box 64, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3172
    Grant 9800250, University of Kentucky Research Foundation, $525,000 to field test arts-infused, integrated curricula and related teacher professional development for middle grades and evaluate effects on teaching and learning.
  - City Year, 9900191, 1999 September 13-2002 September 13 (Box 64, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 3177
    Grant 9900191, City Year, $225,000 to implement service-learning activities in the Philadelphia public schools.
  - Detroit 300, 20000196, 2000 September 10-2002 September 10 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3178
    Grant 20000196, Detroit 300, $420,000 to support the Detroit 300 Education Program, School participation Project as part of Detroit's tricentennial celebration in 2001.
  - South Florida Annenberg Challenge, 9700207, 1997 December 9-2002 December 9 (Box 67, Folder 1-2)
    Knight File Number - 3191
    Grant 9700207, South Florida Annenberg Challenge, $1,000,000 for matching support to promote substantial improvement in the achievement of students in the public schools of Dade, Broward and Palm Beach counties through innovative school/community partnerships. (2 folders)
  - Institute for Research on Higher Education, 9900071, 1999 June 15-2003 June 15 (Box 72, Folder 10)
    Knight File Number - 3246
    Grant 9900071, Institute for Research on Higher Education, $2.21 million for the Knight Higher Education Collaborative, a network of over 160 colleges and universities working cooperatively with innovative consultants and technical assistance providers to accelerate the pace for accomplishing purposeful change.
  - New American Schools, 20010250, 2001 September 11-2003 September 11 (Box 74, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3262
    Grant 20010250, New American Schools, $2 million, to support New American Schools' Plan to achieve financial self-sufficiency while continuing its efforts to promote and implement comprehensive, research-based school reform design models.
  - New American Schools, 20010250 - NAS Academy on Parent, Educator and Community Engagement, 2001 October 11-13 (Box 74, Folder 3)
  - University of Kansas Medical School-Wichita, 20020402, 2002 December 10-2003 December 10 (Box 75, Folder 13)
    Knight File Number - 3281
    Grant 20020402, University of Kansas Medical School-Wichita,$91,000 to identify needs and gaps in service delivery that will assist the community in developing strategies to improve children's readiness to begin school.
  - University of Miami, 20000053, 2000 March 14-2003 March 14 (Box 76, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 3322
    Grant 20000053, University of Miami, $2.1 Million, for the school of Architecture to develop a mid-career program of professional development in community building.
  - WorkForce Silicon Valley, 20000009, 2000 March 14-2003 March 14 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 3329
    Grant 20000009, WorkForce Silicon Valley, $300,000 for a partial challenge for Techforce Tomorrow, a comprehensive effort to enhance information technology career opportunities.
  - Teach for America, 20010252, 2001 September 11-2004 September 11 (Box 81, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 3407
    20010252 for $3 milliion to Teach for America, to expand Teach for America's teaching corps to 4,000 by the year 2004.
- Emergency, 1989-2006; 8; 4.94 Cubic Feet 13 letter document boxes
  - Crisis Assistance Ministry, 89-176, 1989 October 2-1990 October 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1202
    Grant 89-176, $50,000.00, for emergency assistance to victims of Hurricane Hugo.
  - American Red Cross, Greater Miami Chapter, 92-156, 1992 August 27-1993 August 27 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1164
    Grant 92-156, $1,000,000.00, for emergency disaster relief in South Florida especially Dade County, following Hurricane Andrew.
  - Center for Haitian Studies Inc., 92-229, 1992 November 13-1993 November 13 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1181
    Grant 92-229, $50,000.00, to provide counseling, case management and referral services to Haitians in South Florida affected by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Coalition of Florida Farmworkers Organizations Inc., 92-232, 1992 November 13-1993 November 13 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    Knight File Number - 1191
    Grant 92-232, $51,000.00, for two community outreach workers to provide assistance to immigrants affected by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Family Counseling Services of Greater Miami, 92-224, 1992 October 19-1993 October 19 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1220
    Grant 92-224, $16,635.00, to establish a field office trailer to temporarily replace the south office that was completely destroyed by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Girl Scout Council of Tropical Florida Inc., 92-228, 1992 November 13-1993 November 13 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1229
    Grant 92-228, $33,859.00, for a hurricane relief before-and-after school program at eight schools in South Dade.
  - The Salvation Army of Dade County, Florida, 92-330, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    Knight File Number - 1801
    Grant 92-330, $500,000, to construct a volunteer village to provide temporary housing for individuals assisting in the hurricane recovery effort.
  - Samaritan's Purse, 92-331, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1799
    Gramt 92-331, $200,000, for the Hurricane Andrew home rebuilding program.
  - American Littoral Society, 93-5, 1993 February 11-1994 February 11 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1275
    Grant 93-5, $71,900.00, for start-up costs for an ecological restoration project in the aftermath of hurricane devastation at Cape Florida State Recreation Area.
  - Boys Scouts of America (South Florida Council), Miami, 93-343, 1993 December 14-1994 December 14 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1293
    Grant 93-343, $282,000.00, for second-year salary costs for nine neighborhood service coordinators and a project director for the South Dade Youth Coalition.
  - Children's Home Society of Florida (Southeastern Division), 93-344, 1993 December 14-1994 December 14 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 1302
    Grant 93-344, $50,000.00, to prepare residential facilities to withstand future hurricanes. To be used for storm shutters at the new American Children's Home and McLamore Center.
  - Dade Marine Institute, 93-4, 1993 February 11-1994 February 11 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1330
    Grant 93-4, $50,000.00, to build a permanent facility in Oleta River State Park to replace trailers destroyed by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Florida City, 93-83, 1993 March 22-1994 March 22 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Knight File Number - 1223
    Grant 93-83, $200,000.00, for the design and working drawings for a new City Hall building to replace the City Hall destroyed by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Florida International University Foundation, 93-7, 1993 February 11-1994 February 11 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1224
    Grant 93-7, $31,600.00, to supplement previous support for a jointly sponsored conference on the lessons of Hurricane Andrew.
  - Greater Miami Jewish Federation, 93-3, 1993 February 11-1994 February 11 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1366
    Grant 93-3, $50,000.00, to maintain a multi-service community hurricane Andrew recovery center. Established by the federation in September as a one-stop center to assist people in the northern part of the hurricane-damaged area of South Dade. Located at the Dave and Mary Alper Jewish Community Center in South Dade, the hurricane recovery center provides assistance with diverse problems, including home dislocation, access to insurance and FEMA funds, job loss and family stresses.
  - Habitat for Humanity of Greater Miami, 93-358, 1993 December 14-1994 December 14 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    Knight File Number - 1368
    Grant 93-358, $300,000.00, for a project to build homes in Cutler Ridge/South Miami Heights for low-income familites affected by Hurricane Andrew.
  - Helping Miami Rebuild Inc., 93-240, 1993 September 21-1994 September 21 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    Knight File Number - 1373
    Grant 93-240, $25,000.00, to help continue the One Stop Center to provide rebuilding assistance to victims of Hurricane Andrew.
  - Interfaith Coaltion for the Andrew Recovery Effort Inc., 93-176, 1993 July 15-1994 July 15 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 1382
    Grant 93-176, $100,000.00, to continue a home rebuilding program and volunteer campsite previously operated by Samaritan's Purse.
  - Interfaith Coalition for the Andrew Recovery Effort Inc., 93-243, 1993 September 21-1994 September 21 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1381
    Grant 93-243, $140,000.00, to continue a volunteer campsite to support home rebuilding in South Dade.
  - Gulf Coast Community Foundation, 20050251, 2005 September 19-2006 October 1 (Box 92, Folder 3)
    Knight File Number - 4134
    Gulf Coast Community Foundation, grant #20050251, $1,000,000. To partially fund the Governor's Commission for Recovery, Rebuilding and Renewal.
  - Internews Network, 20050027, 2005 April 1-2006 April 1 (Box 93, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 4112
    Internews Network, 20050027, $500,000. To rebuild radio journalism in northwest Indonesia in the wake of the Indian Ocean tsunami.
  - Internews Network, 20050027 - Emergency Broadcasting: A Rapid Response Communications System for Aceh Disaster Relief (Box 93, Folder 4)
    Written on back: "On December 26, 2004, an earthquake and tsunami devastated Aceh in North Sumatra. The disaster created over 500,000 Internally Displaced Persons (IDPs). At the same time, it devastated most of Aceh's broadcasting outlets, plunging large swathes of the population into an information vacuum.
    Within weeks of the tsunami, Internews assembled a team of Indonesian and international staff to bring immediate assistance to the media and Aceh. The team found out that the recovery effort in Aceh lacked locally relevant information flow between citizens, organizations, and government agencies.
    Internews' Aceh Emergency Broadcasting project is a rapid response information service for the people of tsunami-ravaged Aceh, using radio and effective technologies to get urgent survival information to the over 4 million residents of Aceh and 500,000 IDPs.
    Internews has worked with local media in Indonesia for more than seven years, in work ranging from radio and TV production to conflict reporting and journalism training."
  - The Salvation Army (Alabama, Louissiana and Mississippi Divisional Headquarters), 20050159, 2005 September 1-2006 September 1 (Box 96, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 4121
    The Salvation Army (Alabama, Louisiana and Mississippi Divisional Headquarters), 20050159, $500,000. For post-Hurricane Katrina relief efforts in Harrison County, Miss.
- Journalism, 1986-2016; 9; 37.6 Cubic Feet 99 letter document boxes
  - American Society of Newspaper Editors Foundation Inc., 86-48, 86-104, 1986 September 18-1987 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Knight File Number - 3025
    Grant 86-48, $20,000 for assistance in financing its ambitious 1886-87 minorities program. Grant 86-104, $10,000 for general support of the Journalism Exchange Program at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy at Tufts University.
  - Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, 89-284, 1989 October 1-1990 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Knight File Number - 1409
    Grant 89-284, $146,608.00, to produce a television documentary on the national scandal in intercollegiate athletics.
  - Northwestern University, 88-271, 1988 December 15-1990 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1486
    Grant 88-271, $1,975,800.00, for the establishment of a Newspaper Management Center at Northwestern.
  - The Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press, 87-147, 1987 September 30-1991 September 30 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Knight File Number - 1827
    Grant 87-147, $182,500.00, for two freedom of information projects, including a five-year provision of necessary computer-assisted legal research.
  - University of North Dakota, 92-274, 1992 December 15-1993 December 15 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    Knight File Number - 1778
    Grant 92-274, $108,355, to establish an Indians into Journalism Initiative in the School of Communication
  - International Center for Journalists, Inc., 93-169, 1993 June 15-1994 June 15 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    Knight File Number - 1245